<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Axel Vanherle</title><link>https://axelvanherle.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Axel Vanherle</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><managingEditor>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</managingEditor><webMaster>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://axelvanherle.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>From Zero to DNS Hero; My Journey Setting Up a Blog with a Custom Domain</title><link>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/22-02-23_zerotodnshero/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</author><guid>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/22-02-23_zerotodnshero/</guid><description>I am excited to announce that we have a new website link! Our website can now be found at https://axelvanherle.xyz. In this post, I will share my journey of setting up a custom domain and playing around with DNS. So, without further ado, here is &amp;ldquo;From Zero to DNS Hero; My Journey Setting Up a Blog with a Custom Domain.
So for a while now, I have been interested in setting up my own website or, at the very least, learning how to do so.</description></item><item><title>Breaking Down the Code; Creating a P2P Chat Client with C++ and QTNetwork.</title><link>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/21-02-23_p2ptcpchatclient/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</author><guid>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/21-02-23_p2ptcpchatclient/</guid><description>In this blog post, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore how to create a peer-to-peer chat client using C++ and QTNetwork. This chat client allows users to connect with each other using the TCP protocol, communicate through sending and receiving messages, and receive a list of connected peers on first connect. The chat client is designed to be extensible, with new peers being added dynamically, and with the ability to send and receive messages to and from all connected peers.</description></item><item><title>How i got this website up and running.</title><link>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/20-02-22_howigotthisup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</author><guid>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/20-02-22_howigotthisup/</guid><description>Hello, this post is an explanation of how I got this website up and running.
If you are reading this, the chances are that it is hosted on GitHub Pages. While there are numerous web-hosting options available, I preferred GitHub Pages for this project because of my prior experience with it. Additionally, it enables me to publish posts efficiently as I only have to place a markdown file in the correct folder, and GitHub actions, in combination with Hugo, do the rest of the work.</description></item><item><title>My first post!</title><link>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/20-02-22_myfirstpost/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</author><guid>https://axelvanherle.github.io/post/20-02-22_myfirstpost/</guid><description>My first ever post on this blog!
It&amp;rsquo;s not really my first post ever, this is just a small test to see if everything is working correctly. i sometimes edit this post to see if everything works after an update, so if you see something odd; this is why. 1</description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://axelvanherle.github.io/page/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</author><guid>https://axelvanherle.github.io/page/about/</guid><description>Welcome to my blog! First, I want to make it clear that my intention is not to boast or instruct anyone. Rather, I am here to share my passion for writing and to document my experiences for future reflection. Of course, if my content happens to be helpful or engaging for others, that&amp;rsquo;s an added bonus.
As a student of electronics ICT, or computer engineering as it&amp;rsquo;s more commonly referred to, I am always seeking to learn about the latest advancements in technology and how they can be applied to real-world challenges.</description></item><item><title>Projects</title><link>https://axelvanherle.github.io/page/projects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>axelvanherle@outlook.com (Axel Vanherle)</author><guid>https://axelvanherle.github.io/page/projects/</guid><description>test sdfsdf
test sdfsdf
test sdfsdf
test sdfsdf</description></item></channel></rss>